<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html
xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
xmlns:bknr="http://bknr.net/"
xmlns:ruinwesen="http://ruinwesen.com/"
lang="en">

<ruinwesen:html-header title="MidiDuino Library FAQ"/>

<body>
<div class="container">
  <ruinwesen:header/>
  <ruinwesen:navigation/>

<div class="content">
  <ruinwesen:banner/>
			<div class="contenttext">
<div style="clear:both">
  </div>

			
				<div class="product">
					<div class="producttitle">MIDIDUINO FAQ</div>
					<div class="banner2" align="center"><img src="/images/mididuino-banner-slim.png" alt="Banner"/></div>

<h3 class="title">What's the MiniCommand and the MidiDuino software environment?</h3>
<p>All the software included in the MidiDuino library was originally
written for the Ruin &amp; Wesen MIDI controllers, the first one available
being the MiniCommand. These controllers offer a complete hardware
MIDI Controller development environment, and use a custom version of
the Arduino environment for programming. The MIDI code written for
these devices was then ported over to the standard Arduino.<br/><br/>

The development environment used to program the MiniCommand is also
called MidiDuino, in contrast to the MidiDuino library, which is what
you have just downloaded. Check out the MiniCommand on
<a href="http://ruinwesen.com/digital">our digital page</a> .</p>

<h3 class="title">Can I send MIDI directly over the USB serial cable?</h3>

<p>Yes, but you have to use a program to convert the serial data to
MIDI data. On linux, you have MidiBang
(http://code.google.com/p/midibang/). Under MacOSX, you can use the
ardrumo software (http://code.google.com/p/ardrumo/) or Serial MIDI
Converter
(http://www.spikenzielabs.com/SpikenzieLabs/Serial_MIDI.html).  Under
Windows, you can use s2midi (http://www.memeteam.net/2007/s2midi/).
Be sure to disconnect these programs before uploading a new sketch to
the Arduino, as they will interfere.</p>


<h3 class="title">Why does my Arduino time out when programming?</h3>

<p>Check if the RX wire is connected to the input MIDI
circuit. Disconnect it before programming.</p>


<h3 class="title">Why is setTempo() not doing the right thing?</h3>

<p>We are aware of that and will fix the correct tempo settings in a
future version.</p>


<h3 class="title">Why does my sketch not seem to work when I use the MD library?</h3>

<p>That's because MD uses too much RAM for the 1kB of the Arduino
Atmega328. Wait for a future release to be able to use the MD
functionality.</p>


<h3 class="title">Why can't I send MIDI in the setup() function?</h3>

<p>You have to enable interrupts before sending data on the serial
interface, as it uses a buffered output. If you want to
send MIDI from the setup(), call sei() before sending the MIDI
data. Be sure to do this at the end of the setup() routine. </p>

				</div>

		
			</div>
			
<ruinwesen:footer/>
</div>	

</div>
<ruinwesen:google-analytics/>

</body>
</html>
